Guide to the Bernhard Knollenberg Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Correspondence (Chronological), 1560-1943; Series I; 5.5 linear feet (13 Boxes)
  - Note of account payable to Benedict Arnold by Dr. Jacob Thompson. Photostat of Original, Undated[1778] (Box 3, Folder 209)
  - AL, Horatio Gates to General Thomas Conway; letter will not be forwarded to Conway, General Lee reprimanded by Washington; Dean's accusation of conspiracy between the Lee brothers. Tells Conway to do well at the French. Court. Photographic Copy, 1779 January 2 (Box 3, Folder 210)
  - Order by Peter Chester, Governor of West Florida, to Elias Durnford, surveyor, to survey 200 acres for William Rogers three miles north of Pensacola, 1779 January 18 (Box 3, Folder 211)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Col. Jeremiah Wadsworth; chartering of vessels to carry rice from South Carolina not successful; wants to know how to obtain chartered vessels, 1779 February 23 (Box 3, Folder 212)
  - ALS, Thomas Conway to [?]; forwarding of a letter from Richard Peters, complains of hard work, and doing the best he can. Photograph of Original, 1779 March 22 (Box 3, Folder 213)
  - ALS, Lieut. Governor N. Bee (South Carolina) to [?]; difficult finding men to man the war gallies; exchange of prisoners discussed with names mentioned, 1779 March 31 (Box 3, Folder 214)
  - ALS, Jean Clement (Paris) to Horatio Gates; talk of the strength of the French fleet, the possibility of invading England. Photostat of Original, 1779 June 2 (Box 3, Folder 215)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; has not received Panton's letter; Panton still has fifteen pounds to draw on, hope that the Rebels will be beaten and legal government restored, so all can join against the French and Spanish. With Photostat of Original, 1779 June 25 (Box 3, Folder 216)
  - AL, Mr. Law Stillman to Dr. John Morgan (Philadelphia); vindication of Morgan, birth of a daughter to his sister; the death of a boy in town, the forwarding of the sermon preached at the last General Court, 1779 July 18 (Box 3, Folder 217)
  - AL, Horatio Gates to John Adams inquiring as to who Jean Clement really is, 1779 August 20 (Box 3, Folder 218)
  - ALS, John Adams to Elbridge Gerry; things in Europe look favorable to America, wants to know who was for and who against his appointment. Photostat of original, 1779 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 219)
  - ALS, John Buss to Stephen Buss; family talk, 1779 October undated (Box 4, Folder 220)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth of Weathersfield; Mrs. Greene had a baby boy; problems with the engineering officers; need of money but none in sight, 1780 February 8 (Box 4, Folder 221)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; need of money is desperate; people won't pay taxes, all is disorder, Congress thinking of turning the Army to the States. Congress and the Army are feuding. Blasts against Roger Sherman, urges Wadsworth to run for Congress, 1780 February 12 (Box 4, Folder 222)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; describing the voyage to England, hopes to obtain Panton's release from prison. With Photostat of Original., 1780 February 22 (Box 4, Folder 223)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; food is scarce, no money to pay expenses of express riders, the coming campaign has no field equipage or support, 1780 March 2 (Box 4, Folder 224)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Mr. Royal Flint; Great Britain will not give up the fight until she loses mastery of the sea. All are divided on the funding policy. The sad state of America and its gloomy prospects leads to fear of trouble at home, 1780 March 3 (Box 4, Folder 225)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; public affairs are growing worse, fear revolution; Wadsworth should go into politics, 1780 March 17 (Box 4, Folder 226)
  - Invoice for merchandise for Edward Bancroft consigned to J. Holker, French Consul at Philadelphia, 1780 March 18 (Box 4, Folder 227)
  - ALS, John Adams to Horatio Gates; introduction of Lafayette's brother, the Viscount de Noailles; asks for information regarding the plan of attack against New York. Photostat of Original, 1780 March 18 (Box 4, Folder 228)
  - Invoice of merchandise in a trunk shipped to Philadelphia, 1780 March 18 (Box 16)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; growing feeling of revolution; no money to buy supplies; Charlestown still safe, 1780 May 8 (Box 4, Folder 230)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; offer of contract for procuring horses for French Army; Charlestown has fallen; British are at Elizabeth Town, 1780 June 11 (Box 4, Folder 231)
  - ALS, W. Temple to Samuel White; letter had been opened; also no one authorized to draw on Temple's account, 1780 June 19 (Box 4, Folder 232)
  - Notes of payment of 12 pounds ten shillings to Major General B. Arnold. David Hopkins to Dairel Lenox, Merchant, Philadelphia, 1780 June 23 (Box 4, Folder 233)
  - ALS, C. Batwell to George Panton; riots in London; colonies will be restored; French squadron is being followed by the British; missionaries will be taken care of in England if the Church falls. With Photostat of Original, 1780 July 5 (Box 4, Folder 234)
  - ALS, Governor Jonathan Trumbull of Conn. to Treasurer John Lawrence; orders him to press the collection of taxes, 1780 July 8 (Box 4, Folder 235)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; 40,000 French are coming; Washington has a plan of attack against New York; feels the states won't furnish necessary men or supplies; gives advice on type of horses to buy, 1780 July 12 (Box 4, Folder 236)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; French fleet has arrived; if each state fears doing more than its share, little will be accomplished. Roger Sherman is attempting to weaken the army, 1780 July 15 (Box 4, Folder 237)
  - ALS, Nathaniel Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; letter to the Committee; argument with French representative; need of supplies for New York expedition, 1780 July 22 (Box 4, Folder 238)
  - ALS, Lord George Germain to Governor Haldriram; Fall of South Carolina; British action in South stopped attempted attacks on Canada, Governor is not to open correspondence directed to the King or one of his officers, 1780 August 8 (Box 4, Folder 239)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; glad Wadsworth gave up the supplying of the French troops; Greene out of Quarter Masters Corp and glad of it, 1780 August 12 (Box 4, Folder 240)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; Congress may strip Greene of rank for leaving Quarter Masters job; Sherman is working to hurt Greene, 1780 August 18 (Box 4, Folder 241)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to John Hancock; tells of his defeat at Camden, 1780 August 28 (Box 4, Folder 242)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; no dismissal of Greene; Army not happy that Timothy Pickering will be taking over Quarter Master's post; we can't supply the second part of the French fleet, 1780 August 29 (Box 4, Folder 243)
  - ALS, Mr. Batwell to George Panton; capture of some French vessels; loss of most of the British East and West India fleet; Parliament is dissolved; all is electioneering, 1780 August 29 (Box 4, Folder 244)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; chides Panton for not writing; Peru is in rebellion; tells of movement of British, fleet; fear for Southern army if it's not reinforced. With Photostat of Original, 1780 October 16 (Box 4, Folder 245)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; announcement of Greene's appointment to command the Southern Army, 1780 October 16 (Box 4, Folder 246)
  - Notice that Abner Pearce has procured a man to serve in his place, signed J. Winkley, Capt. Commander, 2nd Connecticut Infantry, 1780 October 22 (Box 4, Folder 247)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; Cornwallis' victory; new Parliament met; record of the King's speech, 1780 November 1 (Box 4, Folder 248)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to. George Panton; asks how to handle Panton's money in England; French should not be allowed to stay at Rhode Island. With Photostat, 1780 November 9 (Box 4, Folder 249)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; sorrow for Major Andre; relates moves of British land and sea forces; British politics are slowly changing; receipt of a letter from the late Andre. With Photostat, 1780 November 29 (Box 4, Folder 250)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; handling of Panton's money affairs; Spain was seduced into the war; French are beginning to tire. With Photostat, 1780 December 1 (Box 4, Folder 251)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; sending a packet of pamphlets. Tells of handling Panton's funds. With Photostat of Original, 1780 December 28 (Box 4, Folder 252)
  - ALS, H. Cooper to George Panton; possibility of a break with the Dutch; capture of French and American privateers. With photostat of original, 1780 December 30 (Box 4, Folder 253)
  - ALS, William Clajon to Colonel Hughes at Fishkill; Clajon cleared of charges brought against him by Gates, 1780 December (Box 4, Folder 254)
  - TLS, Josiah Blakely from William Kenyon; talks of Benedict Arnold and some of his mercantile transactions, [1780] (Box 4, Folder 255)
  - ALS, B. Seixas to Aaron Lopez; concerns the loan of money and rate of exchange, [1780] (Box 4, Folder 256)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; discusses Panton's investments, outfitting of British privateers against the Dutch. With Photostat, 1781 January 1 (Box 4, Folder 257)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; reports on Dutch War and looks to the future; problems in the West Indies. Parliament in recess. With Photostat, 1781 January 3 (Box 4, Folder 258)
  - A coded message from French Ambassador Destouches to [?]; reports the British in Virginia, the inhabitants are trying to save their goods, not fight. Photostat of the original in French, 1781 January 16 (Box 4, Folder 259)
  - ALS,[N. Greene] to John Adams; tells of the problems encountered in taking up command of the Southern Army. Photostat of Original, 1781 January 28 (Box 4, Folder 260)
  - ALS, Rochambeau to Washington; tells of destructive gale, hope of having Admiral Destouches' fleet break communication between New York and the South. Photostat of Original, 1781 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 261)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; talks of stock purchases and bills paid by Chandler for Panton. With Photostat of Original, 1781 February 4 (Box 4, Folder 262)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; the minority has no chance in this world; national credit high, reinforcements being sent to British garrisons around the world. With Photostat of Original, 1781 February 6 (Box 4, Folder 263)
  - ALS, M. Destouches to [?]; the French will send vessels and reinforcements into Chesapeake to support. the Americans. Original French letter, 1781 February 20 (Box 4, Folder 264)
  - ALS, G. Washington to Colonel Dayton; instructing the spies to keep close watch on the British in New York, especially up river, while Lafayette's troops are absent. Photostat of Original, 1781 February 22 (Box 4, Folder 265)
  - ALS, George Washington to Joseph Jones; if the French sent their whole force to Virginia Arnold's corps would have been destroyed; we should make the most of their assistance without reminding them of their mistakes; need for joint land/sea operations. Photostat of Original, 1781 March 24 (Box 4, Folder 266)
  - ALS, G. Washington to William Fitzhugh (p. 2&3 only); The army is wasting time and money until the states agree to support it; waiting to hear from Southern army. Photostat of Original, 1781 March 25 (Box 4, Folder 267)
  - ALS, G. Washington to General Armstrong; complains that the French didn't commit themselves enough around the Chesapeake area. Photostatic copy, 1781 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 268)
  - Note due, M. Holker at Philadelphia from Luruz Chaumont of Paris. In French, 1781 March (Box 4, Folder 269)
  - ALS, Theodore Sedgwicke to Jeremiah Wadsworth; introducing Thomas L. Welbuk who is procuring horses for the Frnch Army, 1781 April 17 (Box 4, Folder 270)
  - ALS, Rochambeau to [Washington]; tells Washington that the French didn't receive his orders in time to send a large fleet to the Chesapeake, 1781 April 26 (Box 4, Folder 271)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; rumors of the death of Franklin in Paris; New York seems to be cut off from news from England. With Photostatic copy, 1781 April 28 (Box 4, Folder 272)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; the British Commanders in Chief don't seem to be doing all they can in America. Cornwallis has not been properly supported. French are not going to send men, ships or money of any consequence this season. With Photostatic copy, 1781 April 28 (Box 4, Folder 273)
  - ALS, Horatio Gates to Robert Morris; compliments Morris on his taking over the country's finances; Gates to be reviewed for having lost at Camden; fears design to remove him from his command, 1781 June 3 (Box 4, Folder 274)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; England is quiet, British plan to proceed through Maryland and Pennsylvania; complaint of the poor communication, 1781 June 5 (Box 4, Folder 275)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; difference between time of letters crossing the Atlantic; British battle plans; rumor of Washington's resignation; sea battles reported. With Photostatic copy, 1781 June 30 (Box 4, Folder 276)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; England has had no news for a month of impending engagements; condemnation of Monsieur de la Motte for high treason; rumors from America. With Photostatic copy, 1781 July 30 (Box 4, Folder 277)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; England restless over the lack of action in America; description of some of England's land battles. With Photostatic copy, 1781 September 28 (Box 4, Folder 278)
  - ALS, P. Cortland to [?]; describes the events leading to Cornwallis' surrender. Photostatic copy, 1781 October 17 (Box 4, Folder 279)
  - AL, Henry Knox to John Adams; description of the fall and surrender of Yorktown; praise for Greene; good harmony between French and American troops. Draft of letter; Photostatic copy, 1781 October 21 (Box 4, Folder 280)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; Chandler was sick; the investment of Panton's money; comments on the capture of Lord Cornwallis and the death of martyrs for England. With photostatic copy, 1781 November 3/December 3 (Box 4, Folder 281)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; tries to console Panton on the British losses, but fears for lack of British action. With Photostatic copy, 1781 December 3 (Box 4, Folder 282)
  - ALS, William Duer to Leonard Gansevoort at Albany; talks of trade and merchandise, also of Robert Morris's plan to dissolve the various boards set up by Congress, 1781 December 31 (Box 4, Folder 283)
  - Synopsis of the Campaign, 1781, as an aid to understanding the map. Photostat of Original. Written in French with English typed copy (Box 4, Folder 284)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; Britain will not give up America; Br. will field army; Loyalists shouldn't lose hope. With Photostatic Copy, 1782 February 3 (Box 4, Folder 285)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; the removal of Germain from office; no American Secretary; peace with the Dutch is in suspense; provision for the American clergy. With photostat of Original, 1782 February 6 (Box 4, Folder 286)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to [?]; where is revenue to come from but the states? If we don't help ourselves, we can't expect it from others; prices and transportation complaint; tells of how difficult provisions are to come by, 1782 February 9 (Box 4, Folder 287)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; Sir Guy Carlton appointed to Chief Command in America; attempt at defensive war in America. With Photostatic copy, 1782 March 6 (Box 4, Folder 288)
  - ALS, Johann Christian Gerning (a noted Danish entomologist) to his patron; speaks of his health, publications and his entomological work, 1782 March 28 (Box 4, Folder 289)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; new ministry, speaks of how the new ministry and administration will affect England. With Photostat of Original, 1782 April 1 (Box 4, Folder 290)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; change in ministry; New York not in immediate danger. Procrastination has deeply ruined English chance of success. With Photostat of Original, 1782 April 3 (Box 4, Folder 291)
  - George Panton to Thomas Bradbury Chandler [?], London, England, 1782 April 11 (Box 4, Folder 291-A)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; introduction of Rev. Mr. Moore. Batwell is despondent over the fate of America. With Photostat of Oriainal, 1782 Mav 5 (Box 5, Folder 292)
  - ALS, George Clinton to Colonel Philip van Renssalaer; monetary matters, 1782 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 293)
  - ALS, G. Washington to John Hancock; the number and disposition of British troops at Halifax requested, 1782 May 8 (Box 5, Folder 294)
  - ALS, D. Batwell to George Panton; Britain trying to cut French aid; sarcastic letter about the change of command. With Photostat of Original, 1782 May 31 (Box 5, Folder 295)
  - TLS, George Washington to Colonel Olney regarding Ensign Johnson whom Washington has never heard of, 1782 June 5 (Box 5, Folder 296)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; Russia is to join England with 15 sail of the line, because the Dutch won't make peace with England. With Photostat of Original, 1782 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 297)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; concerns Panton's investments and salary due from the Missionary Society. With Photostat Of Original, 1782 July 3 (Box 5, Folder 298)
  - Exchange note to Joshua Loring from Henry Knox carried by General Lincoln, worth $500, 1782 July 17 (Box 5, Folder 299)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; writes of financial affairs and of the relief convoy to Gibraltar and the damage caused by gale and accident to the ships. With Photostat of Oriainal, 1782 September 4 (Box 5, Folder 300)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton;Colonies are being given away by the commissioners in Paris; Governor of New York has not yet handed over the address by Loyalist to the King. With Photostat of Original, 1782 October 1 (Box 5, Folder 301)
  - ALS, Matthew Ridley to (?); from Paris with a discussion of Peace, 1782 October 10 (Box 5, Folder 302)
  - ALS, Gen. Christie to (Allea?) Adam in London; monetary matters; charge of traitor lodged against Christie; also his son mentioned in the newspapers, 1782 October 12 (Box 5, Folder 303)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; state of Panton's finances; prices will fall unless there is a general peace; negotiations at Paris renewed; only Britain has stopped the rebellion from falling apart by internal decay. With Photostat of Original, 1782 November 3 (Box 5, Folder 304)
  - ALS, Peter R. Livingston to Jeremiah Wadsworth; purchase of flour at a commission. Photostat of Original, 1782 November 11 (Box 5, Folder 305)
  - ALS, Matthew Ridley to Governor Morris; if there is no peace so the combined French and Spanish fleets are prepared to fight vigorously both in the United States and in the East Indies, America must be a friend of all, but independent of all, 1782 November 20 (Box 5, Folder 306)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; no stock purchase price too high due to rumor of peace; rumor of peace treaty arrives. With Photostat of Original, 1782 December 4 (Box 5, Folder 307)
  - ALS, Jonathan Williams (B. Franklin's Secretary in France) to Mr. White; "All goes right where my person is, but the Devil gets into everything when my back is turned.", 1782 December 23 (Box 5, Folder 309)
  - Note for receipt of $5 from Timothy Pickering to Abram Slutt; Marvel Slutt; Francis Weldon for carting provisions, 1783 February 3 (Box 5, Folder 310)
  - ALS, T.B. Chandler to George Panton; stocks are rising; preliminary peace signed with France and Spain. With Photostat of Original, 1783 February 5 (Box 5, Folder 311)
  - Receipt for $9 and 17/19 for carting wood. From Timothy Pickering, Quarter Master General, to Abraham Strickbud, 1783 March 1 (Box 5, Folder 312)
  - ALS, Matthew Ridley to Governor Morris; from Paris, final peace has not yet been signed; England is split by parties and factions; problem of refugees;people in America must pay taxes, 1783 March 24 (Box 5, Folder 313)
  - ALS, Mendosa and Brush (merchants) from Mederia to Howe and Colt (merchants), New Haven; open trade exchanging American produce for wine, need for horses. With list of articles and exchange notes, 1783 April 5 (Box 5, Folder 314)
  - ALS, Thomas Sharpe to Samuel Ridout; concerns reading books; family discussion, difficult to read, 1783 April 26 (Box 5, Folder 315)
  - ALS, George Ross to Robert Morris, asking Morris to represent him, 1783 June 16 (Box 5, Folder 316)
  - ALS, G.[underline]P.[underline] to John Uardherded, Esq.; talks of heads and punishment, seems to fear capital punishment for crimes committed at New York. With Photostat of Same, 1783 July 10 (Box 5, Folder 317)
  - ALS, Lord North (Duke of Portland?); asks to admit General Vaughan to the Order of Bath; North had attack of gout, 1783 December 2 (Box 5, Folder 318)
  - ALS, William Livingston to General David Foreman; asks him to find some one to rescue a departed loyalist's --Sir Charles Douglas-- property, 1784 January 17 (Box 5, Folder 319)
  - ALS, George III, King of England; General Order concerning the buying and selling of commissions by second officers, 1784 January 28 (Box 5, Folder 320)
  - ALS, William Gordon (Famous historian of the American Revolution) to (?), concerns the purchase of books, 1784 March 2 (Box 5, Folder 321)
  - ALS, Peter Livingston to (Aaron Burr?); wants recipient to look into Court Records for a bill due, also to pay for sugar sent. Photostat of Original, 1784 April 14 (Box 5, Folder 323)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; Greene in financial difficulties; asks Wadsworth to back his note; asks Wadsworth to buy into Cumberland Island; talks of going into the Spanish trade, 1785 February 3 (Box 5, Folder 327)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; concerns the purchase of Cumberland Island, 1785 February 17 (Box 5, Folder 328)
  - ALS, Charles Thomson to John Lawrence; concerning the question of whether the Court of Appeals still exists, 1785 February 20 (Box 5, Folder 329)
  - Nathanael Greene appointing Jeremiah Wadsworth as true and lawful attorney to sign and dispose of lands. Legal form, 1785 March 26 (Box 5, Folder 330)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to [Marboro]; a description of Cumberland Island and reason for selling part of it, 1785 April 15 (Box 5, Folder 331)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; Greene doesn't want to sell more than one quarter of the island if he can get clear of his creditors, 1785 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 332)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; note drawn on Wadsworth for $300 by Greene to pay John Kean, 1785 May 12 (Box 5, Folder 333)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; trying to sell a vessel to get money; will so journey north, 1785 May 13 (Box 5, Folder 334)
  - ALS, Marquis de Lafayette to [?]; concerns the Society of the Cincinnatus. Photostatic Copy, 1785 June 4 (Box 5, Folder 335)
  - ALS, William Livingston to Messers Arnold and Halsey; there is no Attachment Law at present in New York; it is impossible to attach Silvester Fuller's property, 1785 July 1 (Box 5, Folder 336)
  - ALS, Nathanael Greene to Jeremiah Wadsworth; concerns monetary matters and Nathanael's brother, Griffin; Mrs. Greene is not well, 1785 July 13 (Box 5, Folder 337)
  - Indenture between Robert and Hannah Harris, and John DeLancey and Robert Morris; of land owned by Harris but given over for one year to DeLancey and Morris for one peppercorn, 1785 August 11 (Box 5, Folder 339)